Guide to the Herman Axelbank Motion Picture Film Collection 1896-1977
Hoover Institution Archives
- Reel #30, 10:10:50-10:16:50
  - Trotsky in his office in the Kremlin -- Famine in the Volga Region -- destruction of industrial plants and bridges following civil war -- continued peasant uprisings -- homeless starving children -- small amounts of grain shipped by Soviet government to famine-stricken areas -- grain sacks checked -- refugees in stricken areas flee in search for food -- foraging for food along the Volga -- soup made of weed concoctions -- homeless at railroad stations -- deserted villages -- official Soviet communications -- Leslie's Weekly (1891)-- refugees along the river - dead mother and baby American aid -- American Relief Administration -- American food arrives in Petrograd harbor for transport -- Colonel Haskell -- children saved -- hot water for tea -- field kitchens -- innoculations against typhus -- church treasures taken by commissars for famine relief -- Archbishop Antonin gets credentials of commissar -- Church of the Redemption, Moscow -- Chicago, USA -- "Friends of Soviet Russia" shipments of foods and medication to famine stricken Russians., 1921
- Reel #32, 10:17:28-10:26:19
  - Band plays the "Intenationale" -- mass singing -- Trotsky administers "Oath of Red Soldier" to new recruits -- German junkers plane demonstrated for Red Army in Moscow -- Russo-German cooperation for joint arming -- German "aeromobile" demonstrated to Russians (from Moscow to Sevastopol) -- June 8 to August 7,Social Revolutionary trial in Moscow -- first "show trial" of anti-communists -- Abram Gotz, Dimitri Donskoi, Michael Hendlman, Evgeniia Ratner, Gershenstein, Artemyev, Leekach, Elena Ivanova, and Vladimir Agapov -- parade and mass meeting on Red Square in condemnation of defendants -- Krylenko, the prosecutor -- Rosenfeld and Anderson Nexo, foreign counsel for defendants -- Piatakov addresses hugh mass meeting on Red Square -- Bukharin speaks condemning the defendants -- refreshments -- passes required to enter courthouse -- prison van -- prisoners emerge and are led to courtroom -- infuriated public sits in at trial., 1922
- Reel #33, 10:26:56
  - Stenographers -- judges -- Pokrovsky, the historian -- Konopleva, defendant, testifies -- Dverzhets, Jacob, defendants, testifies -- prisoners dock -- trial concludes -- Kashira, hydro-electic power station at Kashira, near Moscow, completed (during Lenin's illness at Gorki) -- Rykov speaks -- Yenukidza with Rykov, advancing toward camera -- Ostrovsky-Mahlee Theatre, Moscow -- Moscow Art Theatre -- celebration of Theatre Stanislavsky anniversary -- Kachalov -- Mirovich-Danchenko -- Nikolai Ostrovsky (blind) -- statue of Alexander III in Petrograd with new inscription: "ignominous" -- CHEKA training grounds in Kremlin -- execution squads -- firing squads -- Russo-Finnish Punitiv Expedition, led by General Sidiakin, for alleged night attack on Red Army outpost by Finnish irregulars -- Finland border attack by Red Army -- Red Army brigade mounts attack on Finnish border outposts -- Sidiakin hailed in Petrograd victory celebration., 1922
- Reel #34, 10:37:49-10:47:50
  - Lenin seated with Stalin at Gorki -- Red International of Trade Unions -- Red Trade Union International Congress in Moscow -- Lozovsky, President of Red Trade Union International, addresses delegates -- Hillman, Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America aids Russia: takes over 40 Russian clothing factories, introduces American labor-saving methods -- Sidney Hillman, President of A.C.W.O.A., supervises reorganized plants -- Yakivenko, Commissar of Agriculture, makes the rounds of local farmers, discusses their problems and government deliveries of their grain -- Agriculture Commissar with farmers during NEP era -- American tractors sent by "Friends of Soviet Russia" are carefully studied -- August 22,Lenin at Gorki -- Zinoviev speaks at outdoor mass meeting in Petrograd -- Thomas, Albert, French socialist, addresses mass meeting -- Yevdokimov, Chairman C.E.C. of Petrograd Soviet -- Lenin in his study at Gorki -- International Youth Congress in Moscow -- Willi Muenzenberg (Lenin's protoge from the International Youth Federation; later murdered by Stalin), President of Youth International addresses congress -- Lunacharsky, Commissar of Education, speaks -- Lozovsky speaks -- Zinoviev addresses delegates -- September 1922,Lenin with Krupskaia, niece and nephew, at Gorki -- International Womens Congress in Moscow -- Klara Zetkin speaks -- Lenin, Krupskaia, Lenin's sister Elizarova at Gorki -- Congress of People of the Far East -- participation of young Ho-Chi-Min -- women from China, Mongolia, Uzbekistan, Kazakhstan, Afghanistan, Persia, India, and Turkestan, represented at this congress convened by the Comintern -- (Lenin at Gorki (last photo ever taken) -- Lenin on stroll in garden at Gorki -- Lenin seated with Krupskaia on garden bench -- Lenin holding cat -- Lenin walking with nephew, Victor, in garden -- Lenin seated with dog -- Lenin reclining in garden chair, Krupskaia seated on bench -- Lenin in overcoat, seated on garden bench) -- Lenin at session of Party Central Committee in Kremlin, October 5, 1922-- Lenin at his desk in Kremlin, October 7, 1922-- Lenin in Moscow, October 7, 1922-- 5th anniversary of the Bolshevik Revolution celebrated on Uritskii Square, November 7, 1922-- Zinoviev head celebration -- Salutskii, a C.E.C. member of the Petrograd Soviet -- Moscow celebrates 5th anniversary of the Bolshevik Revolution on Red Square -- Trotsky arrives, followed by foreign delegates to the 4th Congress of the Comintern (to convene on November 14) -- Trotsky's opening address -- Red Army generals (later murdered by Stalin) -- parade of Moscow garrison -- foreign visitors on reviewing stand -- foreign delegates to the Comintern: Max Eastman, Louis Fraina, Rose Pastor Stokes, Charles Ruthenberg, Max Bedacht -- naval personnel -- Trotsky salutes the Red Army, Voroshilov behim him -- General Muralov (murdered by Stalin 1936-37) in rear -- Lunacharsky, Zinoviev, Kamenev, on rostrum -- Kamenev and Zinoviev -- Stalin -- Klara Zetkin seated on rostrum -- Stalin turns to camera -- Klara Zetkin -- Radek and his little daughter -- November 14,4th Congress of Comintern in Petrograd -- train arrives with foreign delegates -- Willi Muenzenburg at left -- delegates leave station in Petrograd -- Max Eastman among arrivals, hat in hand., 1922
- Reel #35, 10:48:29-10:58:23
  - Yevdokimov, member of Petrograd Soviet (later murdered by Stalin), greets delegates -- Fritz Heckert, German communist, speaks to welcoming crowds -- Zinoviev speaks -- Felix Kohn, delegate from Poland, speaks -- Lunacharsky greets delegates -- Congress opens at Marinsky Theatre (note Trotsky portrait at upper left proscenium) -- Klara Zetkin -- Zinoviev -- delegates rise, sing "Internationale" -- Petrograd garrison parades in honor of delegates to Comintern (note rickety military vehicles) -- Mars Field, wreath place on grave of martyrs of the revolution -- Congress moves to Moscow for last sessions -- railroad stations display portraits of Lenin, Marx, and Trotsky -- trolleys in Moscow take delegates to Congress Hall (the Tsar's throne room) -- trolleys decorated with bunting and portraits of Lenin and Trotsky -- throne room of the tsars -- Zetkin, Zinoviev, on dais and on extreme right American delegate -- Earl Browder -- group of delegates -- Roy, from India, speaks -- Sen Katayama, of Japan, speaks -- Billings, American negro delegate, speaks -- Azario, from Italy, speaks -- Katayama speaks -- _____, from Bulgaria, speaks -- Trotsky addresses congress -- C.E.C. of Comintern -- Zinoviev and Klara Zetkin -- Australian communist delegates (Crawford and __________) -- Claude McKay, American negro delegate with Egyptian delegate -- Salutskii and Yevdokimov -- Lunacharsky -- Max Eastman and Claude McKay -- Zinoviev speaks -- Lenin attends the Comintern for the last time -- Lenin taking notes prior to speaking -- Lenin addresses the 4th Congress of the Comintern -- Trotsky taking notes prior to speaking -- Trotsky addresses the Congress --, 1922
  - April 17, 1923,12th Party Congress -- Trotsky at 12th Party Congress -- Rykov, seen ascending platform -- Bukharin speaks -- Trotsky, Muralov, at rear., 1923
- Reel #36, 11:00:00-11:09:33 (Videotape 11)
  - May Day in European capitals, May 1st, 1923:London, Zurich, Stockholm, Paris, Berlin, Oslo, Prague -- May 1, 1923,Moscow May Day celebration -- Trotsky, Muralov -- International Workers Aid (Comintern organization) headquarters in Moscow, during Soviet Russia's first agricultural exposition -- Trotsky's portrait on the wall -- tea served free to all -- Rykov speaks -- agricultural exposition in Moscow -- Komsomol (Young Communist League) youth at the exposition -- Chicherin speaks in open-air stadium at the fair -- Krassin, Commissar of Trade, speaks -- "Internationale" sung by 40,000 voices -- organizers of this first Russian fair in 1923 -- free lunches., 1923
- Reel #41, 11:10:11
  - Lozovsky, President of Red Trade Union International speaks -- portraits of "Lenin-child" carried by children everywhere -- Comintern delegates on rostrum -- Rykov, Acting Premier, among foreign delegates on rostrum -- Zetkin, seated, among delegates on rostrum -- Ho-Chi-Min on rostrum -- Felix Kohn, delegate from Poland, waves -- Bulgaria: Sofia Cathedral dynamited by communists -- untold number of suspects including liberals, socialists, executed by Bulgarian government -- Communist Party banned in Bulgaria -- Moscow: "Religion is Opium of the People" on facade of Moscow City Hall -- Sacco-Vanzetti: cause celebre of Comintern, moving American communists to wage nationwide campaign to save their lives -- Stalin, Kaganovich, Molotov, prior to Trotsky's banishment to Alma Ata -- Kerensky in Paris -- Trotsky in exile on Prinkipo Island, Turkey, under guard by Turkish secret agents -- Natalia Sedov, Trotsky's wife, and son, Leon Sedov, at Prinkipo., 1924, 1927, 1928, 1929
- Reel #42, 11:20:12-11:29:12
  - Trotsky visit ruins of Pompei, under Italian police guard
  - November 20, 1932,Trotsky on way to Copenhagen, Denmark -- Trotsky speaks in Copenhagen, November 26, 1932,(soundtrack) to 2,000 audience (labor group) -- Trotsky in France, 1933,under tight security against Stalin agents -- Trotsky in Norway -- Trotsky interned by Norwegian government in 1936 when he denounced Stalin's frame-up trials in 1936 -- Trotsky arrives in Tampico, Mexico, 1937,given asylum by Mexican President Cardenas and invited to live with painter Diego Rivera -- Trotsky speaks in English (soundtrack), denouncing Stalin's falsifications and frame-up trials -- friends of Trotsky guard him at his home in Acapulco in 1939, following an assassination attempt by Mexican Stalinists -- Sylvia Ageloff, who introduced her friend (assassin) to Trotsky in 1940 -- assassin who murdered Trotsky with pickaxe on August 20, 1940 -- reserve weapons found on assassin -- murder weapon -- victim's broken glasses -- nurse attending dying Trotsky -- Trotsky dies in Mexico -- assassin, following capture -- Trotsky's grave in Mexico -- assassin, released after 20 years incarceration, admitted to Cuba and apparently taken off to the U.S.S.R. under guard, 1960.Stalin's 50th birthday in his apartment in the Kremlin -- Kirov, Kaganovich, Kuibyshev, Molotov, Ordjonikidze, Kalinin, Voroshilov., 1932, 1933, 1935, 1936, 1937, 1939, 1940, 1960, 1929; No sound Track on Trotsky Speech; Speech on film
- Reel #47, 11:29:39:01-11:39:50
  - Kalmyks, Autonomous Region of Kalmyk Republic on the Caspian Sea, when it was a flourishing community with collectives and large fishing industry -- Elista, Kalmyk capitol, end of December 1943-- Stalin ordered deportation of entire Kalmyk population to Siberian slave camps -- Kalmyk Autonomous Republic prior to its liquidation., 1936
  - Stalin "child lover", one of periodic filming of Stalin's human side -- Stalin lifts child affectionately -- Stalin entertained by Georgian state troupe -- sword dance -- Caucasian sword dancing -- Stalin portraits everywhere -- song and dance festival in Stalin's native Georgia -- Stalin arrives with Voroshilov -- Molotov, Stalin and Kalinin in front row -- mass dancing.
  - Voting for Stalin -- Stalin votes for himself -- Molotov, Kalinin, and Mikoyan vote for Stalin.
  - Election celebration on Red Square -- sea of Stalin portraits.
  - August 1936,purge trials -- Stalin's framed trials of his oppositionists -- false confessions by victims -- Kamenev prior to his execution -- Vishinskii at purge trials in Moscow -- witnesses and victims testimony -- Vishinskii's assistants -- Piatakov shielding his eyes -- firing squad in the Kremlin.
  - Tchkalov and Gramov flight -- polar flight -- to San Francisco -- San Francisco's reception to Soviet polar flyers -- spectacular feats to muffle sounds of firing squads -- Troyanovsky greets flyers in San Francisco., 1937
- Reel #62, 11:40:31-11:48:40
  - Timoshenko's plane arrives in Kishinev -- Khrushchev greets him -- Timoshenko's hometown folks kiss him and Khrushchev. While Germans overrun Europe, Stalin celebrates 23rd anniversary of Bolshevik Revolution -- November 7, 1940,Red Air Force and armor, poised for Red Square show -- Moscow Garrison at attention, awaiting the appearance of Stalin -- Stalin emerges from Kremlin, greets Kaganovich, Molotov, Kalinin, Voroshilov, and Andreiev -- they walk to the mausoleum -- Stalin and Shvernik -- Timoshenko opens ceremonies -- Stalin and Voroshilov -- Timoshenko -- Shaposhnikov and Budionny -- Andreiev, Beria, Molotov, Mikoyan, Voroshilov, Beria and Shvernik -- Shvernik and Stalin -- Bulganin, Malenkov, Beria, Mikoyan, Voroshilov, Kaganovich. Molotov in Berlin -- Mannerheim with Hitler., 1940
  - April 1941, on eve of Hitler's onslaught, First Degree Stalin Prize awarded to Olga Lepeshinskaia, premiere danseuse of the Bolshoi Ballet -- Lepeshinskaia dances (soundtrack)., 1941
  - May 1, 1941, Stalin celebrates May Day on Red Square -- heavy armor poised for big parade -- German military attaches last look at Soviet tanks and planes -- Stalin struts to podium, flanked by Molotov and Voroshilov, followed by entourage.
- Film #152 (open)
  FILM GUIDE
  CODE NO. 614700
  RUSSIA: CZAR TO LENIN
  (30 minutes-black and white)
  Presented by McGRAW-HILL TEXT-FILMS
  FOR USE IN
  High school and college classes in World History and Russian History.
  PURPOSE OF THE FILM
  To depict the events during the years 1914-1920 when the Bolsheviks seized control of the Russian government and fought to maintain themselves in power until Vladimir Lenin had replaced the Czar as the head of that government.
  CONTENT OF THE FILM
  The film tells the story of the Russian Revolution from its outbreak in February of 1917 to November 1920 when the last of the counter-revolutionary forces were defeated. Rare pictures of the fighting and of the personalities involved are used.
  The film story begins with scenes of Czar Nicholas I1 and his family just before the outbreak of World War I. The character of the Czar is brought out and the frivolous ways in which he and his family amused themselves while the country seethed with discontent are shown.
  As a result of the disaster suffered by the army and the hardships endured by the populace, discontent flared into the open. Trouble first began in the streets at Petrograd where crowds gathered to sing revolutionary songs and display banners demanding Peace, Bread, and Liberty! Although the Czar ordered the soldiers to disperse the mobs, the soldiers refused and actually joined the people. A workers' council called a soviet was formed in Petrograd. Four of the Czar's regiments mutinied and placed themselves at the disposal of the revolutionists. Although the Czar sent other troops from the front, they too joined the revolt. The Czar was forced to abdicate.
  The film then shows the events of the early stages of the Revolution: how the Grand Duke Michael Romanov refused the throne, how a government was organized under Prince Lwow and then, later, under Alexander Kerensky. The film also shows the gathering forces that opposed each other under the moderate government of Prince Lwow and Kerensky. It shows the arrival of Lenin and the struggle for power that took place which resulted in Lenin's seizure of the reins of government.
  Scenes showing how Lenin, with the aid of Trotsky, maintained himself and the Bolsheviks in power, and how the war with Germany ended, at Lenin's insistence, on most unfavorable terms, are presented. The treaty of Brest-Litovsk, however, did not bring peace to Russia, for now most of the world was against her. Former allies were dismayed at her withdrawal from the war and shocked at the character of the Bolshevik government. Allied troops landed at Archangel and at Vladivostok. Czecho-slovak war prisoners seized the Trans-Siberian railroad. Within a year fourteen hostile counter-revolutionary armies were fighting against the Soviets.
  For the next three years Russia was subjected to a violent civil war. Ruthless terror and killing became common practice on both sides. The Czar and all his family were shot to death, their bodies burned, and the ashes scattered in a swamp. Lenin himself was wounded by an assassin.
  Of the counter-revolutionary armies the most important were led by General Denikin in the south, Admiral Kolchak in the east, General Bogayevsky in the southwest, and General Yudenich in the northwest. But Trotsky had done his work well; the Red Army defeated each in turn until finally, in mid-November of 1920, the last of General Denikin's troops fled from the Crimea to end the civil war. In the meanwhile, the Allies had tired of the occupation and had withdrawn their troops.
  The infant Soviet Republic with Lenin at the helm had survived. Lenin and the Bolsheviks (now called Communists) could turn their attention to rebuilding the shattered nation.
  BEFORE VIEWING THE FILM
  Historical Background
  The appearance of the Communist Manifesto and Das Kapital
  The rise of the Social Democratic Party
  World War I
  Treaty of Brest-Litovsk
  The Russian Revolution, 1905
  Historical Personalities
  Czar Nicholas II
  Rasputin
  Vladimir Lenin
  Leon Trotsky
  M. L. Kalinin
  Josef Djugashivili
  Prince Lwow
  Alexander Kerensky
  Admiral Kolchak
  General Denikin
  Marshall Budenny
  Basic Vocabulary
  autocracy
  Bolsheviks
  Mensheviks
  despotism
  anarchy
  capitalist
  Soviet
  agitator
  fraternize
  Cheka
  commissar
  Guide Questions
  1. Why are major wars often breeders of revolutionary movements within the nations which participate in them?
  2. Often revolutions which start as moderate movements result in radical developments of either the right or left. Why is this so?
  3. Why is it often possible for a small, well-organized minority to seize control of a nation?
  4. Marx had predicted that Communist revolutions would take place first in the highly industrialized nations. Yet the first successful Communist seizure of power took place in Russia, a relatively backward agrarian nation. Why?
  AFTER VIEWING THE FILM
  Discussion Activities
  1. What conditions in Russia led to the Revolution of 1917?
  2. Why did the Russian army make such a poor showing in World War I?
  3. Why did the moderate governments of Prince Lwow and Kerensky fail?
  4. Why did Lenin submit to the harsh German terms at Brest-Litovsk?
  5. Why did Russia's former war allies intervene and then lose interest?
  6. What were Lenin's objectives for world wide communism?
  7. After the war with Germany was ended, what opposition did Lenin and the Bolsheviks face at home? How was this opposition overcome?
  8. How would you assess Trotsky's role in the Revolution?
  For Further Research
  1. Find out why the Communists were not successful in capturing the governments of other nations which had participated in World War I. Compare this situation with what happened as a result of World War II.
  2. What was Lenin's philosophy of bringing about a communist revolution? Find out also why Lenin turned to Marxism.
  3. Find out how Lenin dealt with the Constituent Assembly when the Bolsheviks failed to obtain a majority of the delegates.
  4. Determine Stalin's role in the Revolution.
  5. Find out what purpose the troops of the United States served in the Allied intervention in Russia in 1918 and immediately thereafter.
  REFERENCES
  Brinton, Crane. The Anatomy of Revolution. Norton, 1938.
  Lenin, Vladimir Ilyich. The State and Revolution. Vanguard, 1927.
  RELATED McGRAW-HILL PRODUCTS
  Films
  Who Goes There?-A Primer on Communism
  Stalin
  Lenin and Trotsky
  The Death of Stalin, Parts I and II
  Nikita Khrushchev
  The Rise of Khrushchev
  Khrushchev and Berlin
  Soviet Russia: From Revolution to Empire
  Nightmare in Red
  The Rise of Soviet Power, Parts I and II
  The Nazi-Soviet War
  The Kremlin, Parts I and II
  A Visit to Moscow
  Meet Comrade Student
  The Soviet Woman, Parts I and II
  Filmstrips
  Communism: What You Should Know About It and Why Soviet Union Series
  Teacher's Guide Prepared By:
  Professor Emlyn Jones, Chairman, Division of History and the Social Sciences,
  Green River College, Auburn, Washington
  For further information on any of the above films and filmstrips, address inquiries to:
  Text-Film Division
  McGRAW-HILL BOOK COMPANY
  330 West 42nd Street New York, N. Y. 10036
- Tsar to Lenin: Max Eastman Version, 1937; 1:06 duration Two 16 mm reels (Film shelf)
  Archive footage documentary assembled by Herman Axelbank, and narrated by Max Eastman, about the Russian Revolution. (Alternate cuts (edits) of this film exist, including one narrated by Valentine Dyall.) Use copy reference number: 79073_f_0006253